chapter 7 is called active inference and
discrete time
chapter 7 is the first in a pair of
chapters with chapter eight on discrete
and continuous time so that they're kind
of like two forks of a river that we
discussed in chapter four and before and
describe the recipe in chapter six now
seven and eight are kind of like one
level deeper going from the kind of all
of uh this group of animals to one level
deeper into its classification scheme on
the way to the specific generative model
for which it's actually given in its
totality but everything prior to that is
about the learning about its principles
and this is kind of on the trunk of the
path to discrete time modeling just like
chapter eight will be about continuous
time modeling what would you add in
okay so I think uh chapters seven and
eight uh really helps to understand
um in a more practical way uh how the
materials from uh particularly chapters
one through five applies in real time
situations uh so uh
even if we somehow didn't get to
understand every details of chapters one
through four uh by when we come to
Chapters seven and eight uh I I think uh
I mean some of those uncertainties uh
about or about our understandings uh can
be uh clarified uh in a in a at least in
a practical sense so uh I believe these
two chapters are really helpful
um in order to consolidate our
understandings from the previous
chapters
awesome well said
so it's going to involve specifying some
discrete time models
7.2 goes into perceptual processing and
the general structure of the chapter is
going to walk through a series of
examples that building complexity
where they first start with perception
in 7.2 introduce decision making and
then describe a few more types of motifs
or cognitive structure or patterns
and also check out step by step and
model stream one where it's built up to
in a different way
so the first example is I'll I'll let
you describe it since it's Musical
okay so uh yeah the first example is
um the situation in which we try to uh
describe uh the performance of an
amateur
um a musician in terms of uh how how we
uh listen to the performance of an
amateur musicians uh in terms of uh the
the predictions we get from our
anticipation of the following notes uh
as opposed to the actual notes that's
being played so uh these kinds of
anticipatory reaction uh listening
reaction to the musician can be
successfully formalized using
um discrete time active inference by uh
putting up uh by by
putting together the matrices a uh for
um the states and uh Matrix B for the
transition between the states um or the
transition probabilities uh which uh
describe in this case describes uh the
probability from going from one note to
the other and uh obviously the
um the actual sequence that's been
played which can be described with uh
The Matrix T so uh and another Point uh
I wanted to point I wanted to mention is
for anyone who has downloaded this
chapter uh before I don't know I think
about June or something
I recommend re-downloading it from mit's
website because uh they have corrected
some of the typos that was previously
present in this chapter particularly in
figure 7.2
cool so
this graphical model
where a person is listening this is a
general perceptual Bayesian framing it's
specified
just like with any other equations
there's a lot to look into but a
indicates the probability of an outcome
given a state
this is saying if it were all
on the diagonal like an identity Matrix
this is kind of a common Motif then
States kind of map to themself so in the
context of
uh
in the context of this model A
represents the mapping between the
observed note and the underlying hidden
true note
and then B describes the transition
Matrix of how those change to time D is
the prior they're specified
figure 7.2
you want to describe it
uh all right so in figure 7.2 or at
least the incomplete version of uh
figure 7.2 we see here uh well at the
upper left uh part of the picture uh we
see uh I mean uh the beliefs about uh
about each note uh at each step at each
time step and at upper right uh we
somehow translate those uh beliefs into
a specific numerical values uh so uh so
instead of just
assigning some continuous values we uh
we we've simplified the situation by
assigning some discrete numerical values
for each note and then
the lower left is supposed to show the
uh the act the free energy gradients and
over time uh or in in other terms uh the
prediction errors uh we get from
um I mean
comparing our predictions with the
actual outcomes uh so lastly uh lower
right picture uh shows uh in parallel to
the upper right picture uh determines uh
the values of these errors so we we can
see both
uh the The Continuous the initial or at
least initial uh continuous assignments
and values and then the further uh
discretizing of the values in order to
get the discrete time situation or the
more tractable at this group time
situations
okay
so it's a general passive inference task
where there's priors about how states
are going to change through time and
then there's real data coming in so
that's the kind of classical predictive
coding video compression Coleman filter
Bayesian setting
7.3 introduces a key Motif which is
decision making and planning as
inference so this is the idea of having
a base graph where the variables can
relate to different things there's high
composability and here the idea is that
a variable is going to be proposed that
we can do inference about that describes
the process of decision making or policy
selection so what would you say about
7.3
so 7.3 is
obviously similar to what we saw in
chapter 4 and if I'm not mistaken even
the topology is exactly the same with
that picture we saw previously so uh
yeah this is the initial setup to or
which acts also as a review
about how these different
components of General palmdp generator
models needs to be
described in in such situations but uh
ultimately the specific case study we
come across in this section is uh the
attempt to model uh the behavior of uh
of a mouse in a teammate so rat and a
teammate so
um especially uh a teammates containing
uh
an aversive stimulus in one arm and an
attractive stimulus on the other so this
is this can act as a kind of toy example
to use uh this kind of probabilistic
modeling to uh
describe these situations
thanks so that leads us right to figure
7.4 here's a visualization of the
situation with the the rat in this case
where there's a
a pleasant and aversive
stimuli
on each end of a decision point
and there's also a epistemic opportunity
to receive some information about the
context that the animal is in
and so that setting is described for
both the case with white on the left
block on the right and block on the left
white on the right
and those are shown in terms of their
differences in the matrices the explicit
specification of the generative model
visualizations show some of the slices
of the B variable
which reflect different transition
probabilities
C represents the preferences which are
expressed over the observable States
D reflects the priors on the different
states that need priors
7.4 what would you say about this
yeah okay so in 7.4 it builds up on the
previous section and adds other elements
that we previously saw in chapters three
and sorry two and four which is how the
exact formulation for
um
expected free energy can be used sorry
variation free energy can be used to
formulate the trade-off between uh the
uh I mean information uh seeking and and
or at least uh between the epistemic
value and information seeking so uh here
it uses uh again that rad example in a
bit more uh more extended and elaborate
form to formulate the epistemic value of
observing a q in a given a given
location
and figure 7.7 is a representation of
this situation
but another situation that's been
uh let me see yeah in 7.9 another case
study discussed here is uh is is the
situation of uh The Psychotic eye
movements and um because it is something
that can be quite successful you just
describe or characterize in terms of
information seeking versus the epistemic
value and the situation here is
uh let me see yeah
shown visually in figure 7.9 which
clearly shows how our visual uh
psychotic eye movement eye movements can
be
um
described in such a way as to as to kind
of trace the trajectory uh of our eye
movement among different regions of the
visual space so
uh and how the information We Gather
from a given region can be can affect
the
um I mean the subsequent trajectories of
our psychotic eye movements so
um
yeah that's basically
the main premise of
this section I guess
nice great
7.5
what would you say about it
okay so uh 7.5
again adds another dimension uh to the
previous formulations and this time we
get to update the generator models by
learning and the
um
so the the generative models for this
situation is a bit more complicated than
the previous ones because it now needs
to account for a mechanism or a way to
update the matrices we had before so in
the previous situations uh we we didn't
account for learning per se but here
we directly update our general sorry
that the word update can be confusing
here we we get to somehow
improve our generative models to
accommodate for these
updating accounts and
yeah so uh this the situation here uh or
the case of study uh uh here uh which uh
somehow elucidate the way that the
learning
um can be a common can be accounted for
uh with these models is uh
again a toy example of a creature uh in
a in a simple world of uh
black and white tiles which kind of
tries to find a a path to reach um a
given destination a certain destination
so it is more complicated than the
situation we had for the rat example
because it only had
um I mean simple trajectories that
needed to
um
a Traverse but here uh the creature or
the agent in this case needs to do lots
of a lot more learning and information
seeking and so on so all the previous
elements uh is kind of combined in this
example and it's a really good example
to see how the different components of
active inference can be
connected to each other
nice
n76 hierarchical or deep inference
first a box 7.3 interlude on structure
learning boxed off topic and a lot to
say but structure learning broadly
refers to learning the structure about a
model
using the same types of methods that you
might to do inference on for example a
more observable
sensor data reading something like that
this section Works towards the idea of
nested inference or or multi-scale
modeling
what would you say about figure 712
so again this situation
is um I think the most complex
situations of this chapter which builds
up uh from the previous sections uh and
this time it adds another layer to
accommodate for
for the inferences that happen
in uh I mean different time steps so in
this case we have multi-time or
multi-scale inference and learning
happening both at the levels of
um sorry at the levels of learning and
at the levels of information seeking so
this
this is represented in
figure 7.12 which represents how uh kind
of this fractal generative model can be
seen as a component in um
this multi-scale bigger generative or
and as a kind of leaf in this bigger
bigger generative model uh so it can be
seen as a lower uh level inference
happening at the leaf level going up to
the hierarchy and influencing sorry uh
collaborating on the whole process of
learning and inference at the higher
level so
um
yeah I guess that's
somehow summarizes this figure so if you
have anything to add
that's that's great
it's an example of the composability
of generative models
what
we've
uh talked about and had Toby Sinclair
Smith describe as the compositional
cognitive cartography
and just what kinds of connectors can
and can't you do
and how can that Motif that the discrete
time model introduces
and then the rest of these features
including action and learning and so on
get layered in on top what can you do
with that
713 gives another example
do you want to say anything about it or
maybe continue on uh yeah so the case
study here is the example of
um linguistic I mean language learning
through reading so not language learning
maybe it's just what happens uh
sometimes
yeah yeah in comprehension so what
happens when reading
um
in a anticipatory way uh the the words
that that comes each after the other so
uh why this kind of situation uh can be
most successfully characterized with
this kind of modeling because it
involves a different scales of learning
and comprehension both at the level of
I mean reading at the level of uh
somehow observing the letters and then
going onto uh the words and then word
groups and so on uh so uh yeah that's uh
really interesting way to uh again
combine all of those elements uh into a
single unified model to see how those
different time scales slow in the fast
time scales
operate together to
to build this more encompassing model of
more incoming generative model of the
situation